Comparison is the next type of operator to
cover.
For this example, I have three player scores
on the first three lines of this 142-comparison
file.
On this first observation, players 1 and 3
have the same score, and player 2 has a higher
score.
Lines 5 through 7 contain print statements
with comparisons.
The double equal sign on line 5 is a very
important point to notice.
Python and other programs use a double equal
sign as a comparison to make it distinct from
a single equal sign, which is an assignment.
To further impress this point, watch what
happens when I change this operator to a single
equal sign and run the code.
We get an error message because you can’t
assign a variable a value in the middle of
a print statement.
I will return this to a double-equal sign
and rerun the code.
The code now runs without error, and the first
statement is False, as the two player scores
being evaluated are not equal.
Speaking of not equal.
Python uses an exclamation point and an equal
sign or what some refer to as a bang and equal
sign to signify not equal to.
I will change the first equal sign to a bang
and rerun the code.
The statement is now true.
Let’s evaluate the second and third statements.
Both statements return a value of false.
Let’s see why.
Player 1 and Player 3 have identical scores,
so Player 1’s score is not lower.
The third statement is false because Player
1’s score is lower, not higher, than player
2’s score.
Since we are covering comparisons, we want
to make sure we understand the difference
between less than and less than or equal to
and greater than and greater than or equal
to.
Comparisons in programming work just like
comparisons in math.
As a case in point, I will change the comparison
on line 6 from less than to less than or equal
to and rerun the code.
The second statement is now true, as player
1 and 3 have the same score.
This change reminds me of a fundamental principle
in programming: fully understanding what someone
wants before writing code.
Often, people may say, “Well, I want to
know if this is lower than that.”
But, do they mean lower, or what they want
could be the same or lower?
That is the difference between something like
less than, or less than or equal to, as we
saw here.
In other words, we need to know the true logic
someone wants for an app to code the app properly
and have the app generate the proper results,
as demonstrated in this example.